No. 99-2064

In The

UNITED STATES COURT OF APPEALS

FOR THE SIXTH CIRCUIT

Cyberspace Communications, Inc.; Abornet; Marty Klein; AIDS Partnership of Michigan; Art on the Net; Mark Amerika of Alt-X; Web Del Sol; Glad Day Bookshop, Inc.; Litline; American Civil Liberties Union,

Plaintiffs-Appellees,

v.

John Engler, Governor of the State of Michigan; and Jennifer M. Granholm, Attorney General of the State of Michigan,

Defendants-Appellants.

Appeal from the United States District Court

Eastern District of Michigan, Southern Division

Honorable Arthur J. Tarnow

BRIEF AMICI CURIAE OF AMERICAN BOOKSELLERS

FOUNDATION FOR FREE EXPRESSION, ASSOCIATION OF

AMERICAN PUBLISHERS, COMIC BOOK LEGAL DEFENSE

FUND, FREEDOM TO READ FOUNDATION, INTERNATIONAL

PERIODICAL DISTRIBUTORS ASSOCIATION, MAGAZINE

PUBLISHERS OF AMERICA, NATIONAL ASSOCIATION OF

COLLEGE STORES, PERIODICAL AND BOOK ASSOCIATION OF

AMERICA, INC., PUBLISHERS MARKETING ASSOCATION

AND RECORDING INDUSTRY ASSOCIATION OF AMERICA

IN SUPPORT OF PLAINTIFFS-APPELLEES AND FOR AFFIRMANCE

MICHAEL A. BAMBERGER

Sonnenschein Nath & Rosenthal

1221 Avenue of the Americas, 24th Floor

New York, New York 10020-1089

Of Counsel, (212) 768-6700

Christy Forth

DISCLOSURE OF CORPORATE AFFILIATIONS AND FINANCIAL INTEREST

Pursuant to 6th Cir. R. 25, the Amici Curiae make the following disclosure:

Are said parties subsidiaries or affiliates of a publicly-owned corporation? No, amici are not corporate entities for which a corporate disclosure statement would apply (i.e., such entities do not have any parent corporations and/or any publicly-held company that owns 10% or more of its stock, see FRAP 26.1).

If the answer is YES, list below the identity of the parent corporation or affiliate and the relationship between it and the named party.

Is there a publicly-owned corporation, not a party to the appeal, that has a financial interest in the outcome? No.

If the answer is YES, list the identity of such corporation and the nature of the financial interest:

Michael A. Bamberger

Counsel for Amici Curiae

Dated: February 3, 2000

THE AMICI

This brief amici curiae is submitted on behalf of a group of trade associations and their members, listed below and more fully described at Appendix A to this brief, that share a deep commitment to ensuring that the Internet achieves its full promise as a revolutionary medium of communication suitable for both children and adults. Amici’s members include authors, publishers, editors and distributors of textual, audio and audio-visual material ranging from books, magazines, newspapers, newsletters and comic books to sound recordings and video games, as well as educators and librarians whose students and patrons desire access to the widest possible range of informative material.

INTEREST OF THE AMICI

Amici’s members (hereinafter "amici") have websites on the Internet and create scholarly, literary, artistic, scientific and entertaining content which appears on the websites of others. They are concerned lest a medium, which the United States Supreme Court has recognized to be a "dynamic, multifaceted category of communication" — the Internet — be turned into a child-proof medium whose "level of discourse" would be reduced to that "suitable for a sand box." This the First Amendment to the Constitution does not allow.

Various of the amici have been plaintiffs in the federal court cases which have uniformly invalidated laws similar to the Michigan statutory provisions before this Court. See ACLU v. Reno, 521 U.S. 844 (1997) aff’g 929 F. Supp. 824 (E.D. Pa. 1996) (invalidating the federal Communications Decency Act) ("Reno I") ("CDA"); ACLU v. Johnson, 194 F.3d 1149 (10th Cir. 1999), aff’g 4 F. Supp.2d 1029 (D.N.M. 1998) (invalidating a New Mexico state statute) ("Johnson") ("New Mexico statute"); ACLU v. Reno, 31 F. Supp.2d 473 (E.D. Pa. 1999) (invalidating the federal Child Online Protection Act) ("Reno II"); and American Library Ass’n v. Pataki, 969 F. Supp. 160 (S.D.N.Y. 1997) (invalidating a New York statute).

In the current environment of rapidly developing and integrating media technology, the once discrete worlds of print, visual and electronic media are discrete no longer. Amici once devoted exclusively to the publication of books and magazines, and production of films are now or soon will be making some of those same materials available online via Internet-capable personal computers and Internet-ready television sets.

Amici draw no comfort from the proposed narrowings with regard to the requisite knowledge and other elements suggested by the State. Faced with potential criminal penalties for guessing wrong as to what a local federal prosecutor might believe is "harmful to minors" in a given community, amici engaged in providing speech for adults will be faced with the constitutionally impermissible dilemma of risking prosecution or engaging in self-censorship.

Under such a regime, frank and provocative discussions, whether generated by "affairs of the state," public health issues such as AIDS and abortion, readings from and critiques of classical and modern fiction, reviews of sound recordings and motion pictures, reader, viewer and listener reactions to literary, music, and television fare dealing in some manner with the topic of sex or sexual relationships, to name a few, may well fall in the category of speech that is viewed as too risky and thus could be forsaken for other, "safer" speech. The necessary effect of the Michigan act will thus be to force speakers to "steer far wider of the unlawful zone." Speiser v. Randall, 357 U.S. 513 (1958).

Rather than being so threatened, amici are constitutionally entitled to participate fully in the growth and development of the Internet. Indeed, amici work every day in myriad ways to fulfill the best vision of the Internet, continually searching for means of responding to the public interest in all manner of information and entertainment, while preserving the wondrously spontaneous and interactive quality of this medium. Through their Web sites, the varied communications entities whose speech interests are fostered by amici are affording the American public access to more information and entertainment, faster and more cheaply than ever before. The functions of publishers’ catalogs, magazine and newspaper kiosks, book and record stores, indeed, entire libraries, are captured in the Web site offerings of amici. And this is just the beginning.

The Michigan statute at issue here threatens to impede this valuable development by attempting to extract from mainstream Internet sites all speech arguably not suitable for minors in derogation of the First Amendment, and imposes this unconstitutional standard on all sites throughout the country in derogation of the Commerce Clause. The court below correctly enjoined that attempt.

The Court Below Properly Ruled That The New Provision Violated The First Amendment

The State concedes that the New Provision is a content-based regulation of speech and thus is subject to strict scrutiny. Brief on Appeal of Defendants-Appellants at 13 ("Br."). As such, the New Provision, like all content-based regulations, is presumptively invalid, R.A.V. v. St. Paul, 505 U.S. 377, 381 (1992), and will be struck down unless the State demonstrates that the New Provision is necessary to further a compelling government interest and is narrowly tailored to achieve that interest. Perry Educ. Ass’n v. Perry Local Educators’ Ass’n, 460 U.S. 37 (1983).

The New Provision Violates The First And Fourteenth Amendments Of The Constitution Because It Effectively Bans Speech That Is Constitutional As To Adults

Because the current state of technology does not allow Internet speakers to exclude minors from their Internet communications, in any practical way, the effect of the New Provision is to unconstitutionally and criminally prohibit adults from engaging in speech constitutionally protected as to them but deemed harmful to minors. Thus, like similar statutes, it unconstitutionally infringes on First Amendment rights. Reno I; Reno II; Johnson.

DECLARATION OF JAN WOLTER

I, Jan Wolter, of Ann Arbor, Michigan, do declare:

1.  I am secretary of Cyberspace Communications, a Michigan non-profit corporation whose primary function is to maintain a free, public-access Internet service called "Grex." The name "Grex" (which means "group" in Latin) is also registered as a d/b/a for Cyberspace Communications, Inc. On behalf of Cyberspace Communications and our members and users, I submit this declaration in support of plaintiffs' motion for injunctive relief against enforcement of Michigan Public Act 33 of 1999 (hereinafter, the "Act").

2.  I have been using and administering public-access computer-conferencing systems since 1983. I am currently the secretary of the board of Cyberspace Communications, and a member of its volunteer technical staff. I served as president of Cyberspace Communications in 1998. Professionally, I am a freelance software developer, specializing in building web sites. I received a Ph.D. in Computer Engineering from the University of Michigan in 1988 and was a Professor of Computer Science at Texas A&M University from 1988 to 1995.

BACKGROUND

3.  Cyberspace Communications is a recognized 501(c)(3) tax-exempt organization that pursues charitable and educational missions on the Internet. We provide limited access to Internet services free of charge, but our primary purpose is to provide a wide range of on-line discussion forums allowing free exchange of information on any topic. Grex has been in operation since 1991.

4.  The Grex system is accessible to the public via the Internet as "cyberspace.org". It is also accessible via a bank of dial-in modems located in Ann Arbor, Michigan. To support our charitable and educational mission, we have made the process of registering to use Grex as barrier-free as possible. Users are not required to pay any fees, nor are they required to give any information about themselves. All accounts are created immediately upon request. This open access policy helps ensure that a wide range of people can make use of our services and bring their viewpoints to our discussion forums.

5.  Grex is active, popular, and has a large number of users. An average of about 200 new accounts are created daily; there are currently about 29,000 active accounts. Users come from all over the world, but the majority of those most active in our public forums are Michigan residents. Many are minors. Because we do not require our users to supply personal information, we do not have complete information about the ages or locations of our users.

6.  Grex is primarily a computer conferencing system, allowing users to post messages in any of over 100 public electronic forums. These conferences are at the heart of our educational mission. Among the topics covered by conferences on Grex are music, the arts, writing, consumer information, housing, finance, small business, philosophy, living with disabilities, men's and women's issues, parenting, pets, computer hardware and software, nature, and role-playing games. There are also non-topical "creative" conferences and a general discussion area. All Cyberspace Communications policies are discussed and developed in a public conference called "coop". Any posting to these conferences typically remains publicly readable for months or years. Postings are censored only in rare cases (for example, if someone posts a dozen copies of the same message we might hide all but one). All conferences can be read over the web even by people who do not have Grex accounts - they are easily readable by anyone in the world who has access to the Internet. The conferences currently contain about 42 million words of text, roughly five times as much text as a typical 20 volume encyclopedia. Roughly 200 new messages are posted to the conferences every day.

7.  Grex also hosts a live chat area, called "party." Messages posted here are short - generally one line of text -- and are seen instantly by other participants, permitting real-time online conversations. Discussions are typically more spontaneous and informal than they are in the conferences. "Party" is especially popular with our younger users. On average over 5000 messages a day are posted in the chat area.

8.  Grex provides many services in addition to conferences and live chat. All Grex users can freely send and receive private E-mail. They can also access the world wide web via a non-graphical browser, and about 1000 users have used Grex to post their own text-only web pages. (Images are not allowed because our Internet connection is too slow and overburdened to support them.) Pairs of users can also open private conversation channels. Users can transfer files of any type to and from Grex, possibly exchanging files with other users. We allow full access to software development tools on our system for those interested in learning programming.

9.  For an operation of its size and scope, Grex's budget is extremely small. All the work of maintaining and enhancing the system is done by unpaid volunteers who contribute services on a part-time basis; we have no paid employees. Cyberspace Communications is funded almost entirely by donations from our users. Our current assets consist of $4,500 in the bank and various old computer equipment. We have about 100 members who donate $60 a year or $6 a month, making them eligible to vote in board of directors elections and for which they also receive a minor increase in Internet access. Our total revenue in 1998 was about $8,200, giving us about 30 cents per user per year to spend. About $7,500 of this was spent simply to keep the system running - rent, electricity, phones, Internet connectivity, and such - leaving us about $700 to spend on upgrades to our service. Except for an unstaffed machine room, we maintain no offices. Although our funding is extremely limited, we value the fact that drawing our income primarily from our users means we are primarily responsible to our users. There are no paid advertisements on Grex.

10.  Grex is an online community. Although for many of our users, Grex is simply a place to get free E-mail or web access, for some 500 people of all ages, Grex is much more than that. It is a dynamic community where they meet and make friends, exchange ideas, and learn new things. Essentially all of our funding comes from donations from this group. Grex is only able to survive because of the dedication of the users who participate in our open forums and believe in the value of our mission.

CYBERSPACE COMMUNICATIONS AND ITS USERS FEAR PROSECUTION UNDER THE ACT

11.  We are concerned that Cyberspace Communications and its users may be at risk of prosecution under the Act.

12.  Our computer is located in Michigan, and many of our users are Michigan residents, however many others are not residents.

13.  We request that our users give information about themselves but we do not require any information to be given. In any event, our system does not give any way of knowing if declared ages, locations, or any other information are accurate.

14.  Cyberspace Communications itself authors only a small amount of material, consisting primarily of publicity information, help pages, and technical documentation for our system. However, there are materials posted on Grex by our users which arguably might be construed as being "sexually explicit matter" under the terms of the Act. These materials are accessible by all users. Since our forums are primarily text-based, most of this is verbal material rather than images. However, users are allowed to import files to their personal areas on Grex, and some use this facility to place publicly viewable images on the system.

15.  Two examples of conference items from Grex which might be impacted by the Act are attached. Exhibit A is a discussion of pornography from the women's conference on Grex. Parts of the discussion might be considered in violation of the Act. To steer clear of arguable violations of the Act we and our users would feel much less free to speak on the subject. Exhibit B is a graphic description of a rape from the poetry conference on Grex. It was evidently posted for artistic and cathartic reasons. The responses show concern, sympathy and support. Many other possible examples could be found.

16.  Although it is not, in general, clear to us exactly what material would or would not be considered sexually explicit, we know for a fact that textual material of any conceivable description could be posted on Grex at any time, by any person. Even if all questionable material were removed from Grex, any person wishing to cause problems for us could post new material at any time. Furthermore, any person wishing to cause problems for us could stifle a discussion by claiming to be a minor.

17.  It is unclear to us to what extent, if any, the Act's exemption for computer network service providers would protect Cyberspace Communications, or what would constitute a good faith effort to inform ourselves of ages of our users or the nature of the material being exchanged among them. Clearly what kinds of monitoring would be expected from us must be different for different types of communications - for example, the Electronic Communications Privacy Act prevents us from monitoring E-mail. What are our different responsibilities with all the different media we offer? Since we allow users to install custom software on their accounts on our system, are we responsible for monitoring new communications systems created by our users?

18.  Our uncertainty about our liability under this law is aggravated by the fact that, as a matter of policy, we allow anonymous users on our system. This is essential to our mission of providing forums for open discussion.

AGE VERIFICATION IS NOT FEASIBLE

19.  To comply with the Act, Cyberspace Communications would have to find a way to ensure that no forum which might contain sexually explicit material can be accessed by a minor. Unless all postings of sexually explicit material were completely eliminated from Grex, this would require verifying the ages of our users.

20.  We have not, as an organization, extensively studied any verification technique. Those based on credit or debit cards would be inappropriate for a free system. Given that we average over 200 new users every day, it is difficult to imagine any verification technique that would not require a full time person and/or a substantial expense, neither of which is within reach of our limited resources.

AGE VERIFICATION WOULD UNDERMINE OUR MISSION

21.  Even if a method were found by which verification could be done reliably within the limitations of our resources, doing so would substantially undermine our ability to pursue our mission of providing forums for free speech and of providing free access to Internet services.

22.  Our current policy of not requiring new users to give us any information is designed to make joining the system as easy and unintimidating as possible. Many people are nervous about getting on the Internet or getting involved in a public forum. Almost any method of proving their age would require users to reveal some significant amount of personal information. Being confronted by such questions would scare off some of the users who could most benefit from our service.

23.  Such a verification procedure would also limit the ability of users to speak anonymously in our forums. We believe that having the option of speaking anonymously is an important part of free speech, and having to identify yourself to the people operating the system would for many, including people such as elected officials or battered women, limit what they were willing to say in public forums like ours.

24.  Segregating minors from other users of our system would also undermine Grex's ability to help young people develop maturity and communications skills. On-line forums are one of the few places where young people can interact with adults on an equal basis. Their ages are not obvious to other users, so they are judged by the content and quality of what they have to say. For young people, it can be wonderful to discover a world where they can be respected and treated as equals by adults simply by sharing their thoughts and behaving maturely themselves. While it is true that there are some risks when young people are mistaken for adults on-line, it would be a gross oversight to ignore the fact that it can also be an extremely enriching experience for them. Grex provides young people positive interaction with adults, interaction that is of educational value and that could not be obtained from a "kids' room."

RESTRICTING CONTENT IS NOT FEASIBLE

25.  Compliance with the Act would force Cyberspace Communications to monitor all forums (because all are accessible to minors), identify "sexually explicit" material, and eliminate it.

26.  Doing this would require substantial labor, especially for the live chat channels which are continuously active 24 hours a day, 365 days a year, and which would therefore require continuous monitoring. It would be practically impossible to find volunteers who would be willing to expend that level of effort and who would be competent to make the difficult legal distinctions between material which is and is not acceptable under the Act. We do not have the resources to pay anyone to do such a job including legal services.

RESTRICTING CONTENT WOULD UNDERMINE OUR MISSION

27.  Even if a method were found by which forums could be monitored within the limits of our resources, doing so would substantially undermine our ability to pursue our mission of providing forums for open discussion on any topic - free speech.

28.  First, any censorship of sexually explicit material for the sake of minors would have to interfere with the ability of adults to discuss such topics on our system, even though such speech is not directly prohibited by the Act.

29.  Second, because of the difficulty of determining exactly what content is "sexually explicit" any censorship by Cyberspace Communications, or self-censorship by our users, would have to be overcautious in order to avoid the threat of criminal prosecution or sanctions.

30.  This chilling effect would impact many useful discussions which touch on sexual topics and have significant social value.

31.  Certainly there has been material posted on Grex which is meant only to titillate or shock. But in our conferences no posting stands alone for long. One user's pornographic posting is likely to be followed by another user's objection to its portrayal of women. When such material appears in an open public forum, community standards - if we understand the term - are readily applied to it, not because the material is suppressed, but because upstanding members of the community are there to respond. When young people are allowed to participate in such forums, it is an excellent opportunity for them to learn to understand and respect community standards on sexuality and other issues.

32.  Young people will always seek out and find sexually explicit material. Our choice is between allowing it to happen in an open forum, where they can hear the perspective of responsible adults, or consigning it to clandestine "outlaw" forums consisting entirely of people interested only in titillation.

CONCLUSION

33.  We have no viable plan or ability to cope with this law.

34.  We have a long history of being good, law-abiding citizens of the Internet. Many of our volunteers would sever their relationships with Grex rather than be associated with an organization whose operation is legally questionable. The loss of many of our most upstanding people would irretrievably harm our community, even if we were never actually prosecuted.

35.  But at the same time, compliance with the law would appear to require that we validate our users and/or censor our discussion forums. For the reasons stated above, we are reluctant to do these things because we believe they would limit our ability to act as a forum for free speech in ways that go far beyond just restricting minors from gaining access to sexual materials. Many of our current volunteers and donors would be uninterested in supporting such a restrictive forum.

36.  But beyond that, doing these things in any meaningful manner, if it is possible at all, would require resources substantially beyond what we now have. Over our eight-year history we have demonstrated that it is possible to provide an excellent service to a very large set of people on a minuscule budget. This Act would make that impossible. It would raise the financial bar so that only organizations large and wealth enough to pay full-time staff people would be able to run public conferencing systems. For us to raise that much money we would probably need some combination of corporate sponsorship, advertising revenue, and user fees. Any of these options could significantly undermine our ability to function as an open forum for free speech on the Internet.

37.  For all of our history, we have been proud to consider ourselves to be the freest forum for speech that can be sustained under the law. If this Act is upheld, we believe that we would either have to shut down completely, or become substantially more restrictive. We do not believe that the benefits of this Act can justify so great an encroachment on the constitutional right to free speech for all Americans.

I declare, under penalty of perjury, that the foregoing is true and correct.

Executed this 25th day of June, 1999.

signed by Jan Wolter

EXHIBIT A

Femme Conference, Item 34

This is a long discussion of pornography that started in March 1995, and continued through May 1997. It is available on the Internet at http://www.cyberspace.org/cgi-bin/backtalk/peek:femme:34.

Most of the discussion is not very sexually explicit, but at several points (including responses 10 and 29) things are said in the course of the discussion that might be considered to be illegal under the Act. The full item spans 157 responses - for the sake of brevity, only the first 32 are included here.

Cyberspace Communications allows users to censor their own responses (the text of censored responses is still publically available, but is moved out of the conferences). One user had used this mechanism to retract some of her postings to this item. With that user's permission we have restored them to this copy, marking them "[RESTORED]".

Item #34 entered by Mark A. Conger(aruba) on Thu Mar  2 22:10:05 1995
 Pornography

 A coworker of mine said today that pornography is not a problem that causes
 men to treat women as objects.  The problem, he said, is that there are some
 really *stupid* men who, after going to a topless bar, conclude that all
 women want to be treated like the women in the bar.  And does it make sense
 to, say, ban or condemn pornography because there are a few stupid people
 in the world?
    I don't know how much of that I agree with, but I wasn't quick to dismiss
 it.  The fact is that most men *can* tell the difference between a picture
 in a magazine and a real person.
    What do the rest of you think?

#1 Paul Kershaw (brighn) on Fri Mar  3 01:08:08 1995:
 Pornography is a problem only inasmuch as it is a symptom of general
 social maliase about sex.

 I stopped playing Doom because I became hostile after playing it.  It
 struck a chord in me.  I have seen it affect others quite the opposite.
 I am not going down to yon Softward Dealers Associates because my
 personality is incompatible with Doom.  I simply don't play.

 My problem with pornograhpy comes about when the models are being
 forced into it.  There is nothing wrong with a woman (or a man)
 creating sexual explicit fantasies for money or pleasure.  The
 issue of objectification leading to rape (especially date rape)
 is one of people not being able to separate fantasy from reality.
 If we ban pornography *for that reason*, we nned to ban Bugs Bunny
 so that people won't go around dropping anvils on each others' heads.

 There... was that suitably incoherent.
   ?

#2 Mary Remmers (chelsea) on Sat Mar  4 08:59:56 1995:
 I consider pornography a slightly different form of masturbation. Instead
 of simply imagining a body for sexual gratification there is a picture or
 photograph or story to help the fantasy along. And as long as the author
 or models weren't coerced into producing the material there is no victim.

#3 Valerie Mates (popcorn) on Sun Mar  5 08:19:40 1995:
 I guess I've run into too many of the type of guy who can't separate fantasy
 from reality, pornography-wise.  I feel very uncomfortable knowing that
 people look at pornography and then interact with me in the real world.  It
 makes me feel that they're imagining me, as a female, somehow combined with
 the images they've been looking at, which (though it's not entirely sensible
 on my part) feels to me like an invasion of my privacy.

#4 Sweet Pea (simcha) on Mon Mar  6 08:33:38 1995:
 valerie, there are men who like real women better than magazine
 glossies who make you uncomfortable...they don't read
 porno magazines but can undress you with their eyes.  I know
 pronography when I see it and I know a gentleman when I meet one.

 Just can't defne either perfectly tho'!

 To me, anything etween truly consenting adults is okay.  Children
 arent' ok when it comes to sex.  But anthing else, I don't care what
 a person looks at.  And I don't think porno makes someone behave badly...
 we're responsible for our actions, thus we can choose our behaviors
 (tho it can affect attitudes).

#5 Dr. Teeth and the Eclectic Mayhem (omni) on Tue Mar  7 01:58:07 1995:
  I've always thought of Valerie as a person, and not a sex symbol. Which
 is typical of my thinking when it comes to women. I think mags such as
 Playboy and Penthouse degrade women from what they should be: People first

#6 Veena Chowdhuri (miranda) on Tue Mar 28 14:44:27 1995:
 Pornography is sexual junk food.  Most guys I've dated have a copy
 of Playboy or some of the other mags, I don't feel that I've been
 treated any differently.  Canada is, unfortunately, is more paternal-
 istic in it's treatement[A

#7 Veena Chowdhuri (miranda) on Tue Mar 28 15:07:55 1995:
 Pornography is sexual junk food.  Most guys with whom I have gone out
 have a copy of Playboy or something like that lying around (I am told
 that they buy it for the articles), but I don't think that I have bee
 objectified as a result.  Canada is, unfortunately, more paternalistic
 with regards to pornography because of arguments that pictures of
 consenting adults participating in sexual activity are somehow demeaning
 to men and women.  I could never understand why.  If a man sees me only
 as a body, I don't want to know him but I don't think that it is
 pornography that makes him a jerk.

#8 Mark A. Conger (aruba) on Tue Mar 28 19:39:13 1995:
 Yes!  That's exactly the point my coworker was making in
#0.

#9 Elckerlyc (clees) on Wed Apr 10 07:19:24 1996:
 Pornography is called considered vile and low when people call it
 as such. It all comes down to values and standards. But I agree
 that pornography is pornography when the human body is
 exploited for money. Money never is and will be a good motive
 to start actions from.
 That less developed people can change their attitudeas a rsult of such,
 is in my point of view a rather sad case.
 Personally I couldn't care less for pictures/movies/videos containing
 explicit sexual acts. Doesn't turn me on a bit. A person, on the other
 hand, might.

#10 Mary Remmers (chelsea) on Wed Apr 10 08:38:35 1996:
 Do you ever go to work in the morning and stay all day simply
 because you need the money?  Isn't that vile, doing something
 simply for the cash-ola?  Heck,  I bet there are wives out there
 fucking their husbands just to keep the home scene from blowing
 up.  Is the wife exploiting her body?  And who are "less developed
 people"?

#11 Mmmm, Lettuce! (beeswing) on Wed Apr 10 19:18:52 1996:
 I dunno. I just don't think that anything positive cAn come from pornography.

#12 Marc (mcpoz) on Wed Apr 10 21:21:46 1996:
 re: #11 - agree - but a lot bad can come from it.  It is dehumanizing.

#13 Mmmm, Lettuce! (beeswing) on Thu Apr 11 01:24:08 1996:
 I think so too mcpoz. What I really woner about is the women (and men) who
 decied to be part of it, by being dancers, in magazines, in movies. From what
 I have heard, dancers can make good money. But why do women have to resort
 to flashing their boobs  in order to do well financially? I don't know about
 it making it influence someone's behavior exactly... but how can it  build
 up a person? How would it make you a better person? It won't. And I learned
 a long time ago that there is a concept of GIGO... Garbage In, Garbage OUt.

 I watched Beavis and Buthead for awhile and realized I was screaming
 "fartknocker" and "buttmunch" when I encountered bad drivers on the highway.
 Not intelligent, I admit. But just 30 minutes a day impacted me that much.

 I hear the "It's ok for adults" thing a lot too. But parents, think about
 it... would you want your son/daughter watching this later on, or being a part
 of it? Hell no. The last thing you'd imagine is your son, whom you raised to
 be moral and appreciate the good in things, slobbering and getting excited
 over a porn movie or in a theater, with women portraying the ultimate sex
 object role. They're going to tolerate what we tolerate.

#14 Mark A. Conger (aruba) on Thu Apr 11 01:56:38 1996:
 Re #11:  How can anything good come out of bungi jumping, or snorkeling,
 or looking at a famous painting?  Do they make someone a better person?
 Yet these are not things we regard with disgust.  Your last paragraph in
 #13, beeswing, seems like a blatant attempt to push people's buttons
 without providing any real compelling arguments.  Kind of reminds me of
 Pat Buchanan.

#15 Mmmm, Lettuce! (beeswing) on Thu Apr 11 17:40:35 1996: [RESTORED]
 Positive things can come friom bungee jumping... you are overcoming a fear
 of doing something you didn't thikn you could do (tho i don't see why!).
 Snorkeling can be positive... seeing a whole new world under the ocean. A
 painting can spark imagination and inspiration. So yes, all these can make
 a better person. How can you compare any of this to a topless bar?

 Do not use Pat Buchanan's name and my login id in the same paragraph. My
 blatant attempt was my opinion, and a way TO MAKE PEOPLE THINK, if they so
 want to. I can't push people's buttons. People make a choice to be angry or
 write um, defensive responses. I don't make anyone feel anything. I find the
 math item in agora furiously irritating and futile, so I skip over it.
 Unless youcan read my mind, you can't ever know my motives, or if I even have
 one.

 And while I'm at it... How abou that restaurant chain Hooters? It seems that
 sexism is ok. I mean if I were to open a restaurant , call it "Darkies", and
 hire only black waitstaff, I'd be shut down in a second! I'd incur wrath frm
 the Black community, and rightfully so. It would be blatantly sick and racist.
 But here is basically the same thing with women, and it's perfectly ok. The
 Hooters I drive by on the way home from work is always packed.

#16 Marc (mcpoz) on Thu Apr 11 21:01:17 1996:
 I think most forms of "risk-taking" are dangerous and it is hard to quantify
 the good from it.  If the adrenaline rush of bungee jumping outweighs the
 risks of becoming an omlette or micro-stroking, then so be it. 

#17 Mmmm, Lettuce! (beeswing) on Thu Apr 11 21:25:59 1996:
 Ah, perhaps. But snoerkeling is relatively safe, as is liooking at paintings.

#18 Mary Remmers (chelsea) on Thu Apr 11 23:25:04 1996:
 I don't tend to think of strippers as garbage.  Or the people who
 go to see them as losers.  Or acts of erotica as immoral.  Or any
 sexual acts between consenting adults as wrong.  Pornography is
 obviously very enjoyable material for some and if a woman is victimized
 by involvement in the industry then she was a victim in waiting and
 if it wasn't porn flicks it would have been something else she would
 have found to abuse herself.

#19 Mmmm, Lettuce! (beeswing) on Fri Apr 12 00:00:17 1996:
 I didn't say strippers were garbage. Just in a very defeating occupation, for
 themselves and for womankind. I don't think they are all victims in waiting.
 Some may stumble into in, some may be lured by the money it pays. I admire
 anyone who works to, say, feed their kids, it's just sad that this is what
 some women have to do in order to earn teh money to do so. beats prostitution
 I guess, but still. And it seems the porn industry is what leads to the drug
 use, the prostitution, and so forth. Not for everyone... but it hapens a lot.

#20 Mark A. Conger (aruba) on Fri Apr 12 02:00:43 1996:
 Re #15:  I still don't see the distinction between the activities I cited
 and pornography.  All are entertainment.  There's no accounting for taste.

 As for my inflammatory comparison between you and Pat Buchanan, of course
 I can't read minds - I call 'em like I see 'em.  Your statement read like
 an attempt at manipulation to me.  The fact that people are responsible
 for their own reactions (I agree with you there) does not mean there is no
 such thing as manipulation.

 I'm afraid I don't see the connection between the Agora math item and this
 one.

#21 Valerie Mates (popcorn) on Fri Apr 12 02:36:13 1996:
 As I see it, pornography hurts women in a way that those other forms of art
 don't.

#22 Mmmm, Lettuce! (beeswing) on Fri Apr 12 10:52:28 1996:
 You don't see the connection in the same way I don't see the connection
 between Picasso and porno. Valerie says it the best in #21. And as for
 manpulation, I can't force that either. People choose to interpret it that
 way and act accordingly.

#23 igor von heiniken (iggy) on Fri Apr 12 18:22:27 1996:
 and, on a similar subject:
 why is it ok to have sex with someone, and ok for you to
 just give someone money, but not ok to combine the two?
 i really do not understand why prostitution is illegal.
 who is it hurting?

#24 Marc (mcpoz) on Fri Apr 12 18:58:52 1996:
 The issue of Porno goes back to how you perceive other people, as humans or
 objects.  I don't know if I can explain this clearly and to everyones
 satisfaction, but consider the following:

 A)  You are a bright young female professional.  You work in an office with
     both men and women.  Your supervisor is a male who is a connoisseur of
     Pornography, topless bars, etc. 

     Would you be willing to trust him in guiding your career development and
     not worry about how he perceives/treats you?  Do you think this person
     will give you the same opportunities as the males?  Is it conceivable that
     he can "turn off that interest" or keep it from clouding his judgement
     when he decides who gets the big promotion, raise, etc? 

 B)  YOu find out that your children's grade school teacher is very much into
     porno.  Do you have second thoughts about keeping them there?

 I guess the point I am trying to make is this dehumanizing has the net effect
 of supporting the sexist activities result in things like glass ceilings.

 Ok, off the soap box again.

#25 Mary Remmers (chelsea) on Sat Apr 13 09:30:25 1996:
 A. Yes, as much as I'd trust anyone I knew so casually or in such
    in limited role.  As long as he keeps his sexual preferences out
    of the work place I have no problem with this.

 B. Yes, as long as he or she is a good teacher what's the deal?  I
    also wouldn't have a problem with a teacher who was a right-wing
    religious zealot as long as those beliefs were kept out of the
    curriculum and didn't become part of the classroom experience.

 Both women and men enjoy pornography.  It's not bad or dirty.  Like
 a lot of things though it's very tempting to see it as wrong for
 society if it's wrong for you, personally.

 And I agree with igor, prostitution should be legalized.

#26 Mmmm, Lettuce! (beeswing) on Sat Apr 13 18:49:21 1996:
 Sex is not bad or dirty, provided it's in a loving, adult relationship. Porn,
 where it's twisted into nothing but selfish gratitfication and objectivity...
 and sometimes abuse... is bad. And reducing the human body down to an object
 with no dignity is dirty. I can't stop a person from buying PLayboy or going
 to topless bars. I can't, and wouldn't burn the porn magazines and videos.
 It does have the right to be there, but it's a sad commentary on our culture
 that it is there.

 Whatt I think mcpoz was getting at (and I aplogize 10,000 times over if I am
 wrong) is that those who frequent topless bars and such obviously like the
 idea of objectifying people, and most often  women. Someone who likes to see
 the woman in the "service" role of a lap-dancing, "what can I do for you"
 arena can't have all that much respect for them. I know women can objectify
 men as well, but look at the ratio of men's bars as opposed to places where
 women could go. ... maybe the Chippendales come by every year or so.
 Coincidence? I think not.

#27 Mark A. Conger (aruba) on Sat Apr 13 21:01:50 1996:
 I disagree 100% with the conclusion in that last paragraph.  It's quite
 possible to be a mature enough person to separate fantasy from real life:
 to enjoy pornography and not objectify people in real life.  That's the
 point my co-worker was making in #0.

#28 Marc (mcpoz) on Sat Apr 13 21:14:24 1996:
 I agree it is "quite possible."  Now what percent of the people achieve that
 separation?

#29 Mary Remmers (chelsea) on Sun Apr 14 00:08:31 1996:
 When a woman is standing over a man, her breasts in his face,
 his heart racing, his penis standing at attention, and his hands
 stuffing his hard earned money into her G-string, who is it
 exactly who is "objectifying"?  Who lords the most control over
 the other, the dancer or the guy sweating testosterone?

 Me thinks we're doing another Woman as Victim item here.  It
 comes so naturally.

#30 Mmmm, Lettuce! (beeswing) on Sun Apr 14 00:08:51 1996: [RESTORED]
 Few. It doesn't make sense to me that "I'll just objectify them  here and
 now." How can one do that for a long period of time, and not have it spill
 over? Enjoying women the most when they're subservient to your needs?

#31 Mmmm, Lettuce! (beeswing) on Sun Apr 14 01:47:29 1996: [RESTORED]
 He is getting of on having a woman be a sex object to him. Will he get teh
 same response if a woman does well in her job? No. So does that mean it
 doesn't t count?

 Women aren't the only victims in this. I feel bad for the men who feel this
 is what they need to do to be satisfied... see it reduced to its lowest level.
 That's what they want to settle for? Don't they have more respect for
 themselves and women than that?

 I don't like it because I don't want to be seen as a victim, and I dont' want
 to see another woman be victimized by porn. And the idea that women are just
 being whiny or playing the victims role by actually getting upset at being
 reduced and demeaned to objects... and being accused of this by other women...
 is a sign that either the accuser does not realize she is in the status she's
 in, or at worst, doesn't care. How convenient to reap the denefits of feminism
 while putting down your own kind and the force that got you where you are.

#32 Marc (mcpoz) on Sun Apr 14 07:59:39 1996:
 I don't have the power of expression that some people have, but I have not
 made my point clear.  I am not disputing this on an individual basis, or on
 the basis of whether men or women are exclusively guilty of "dehumanizing."

 My point was that it has a great societal effect and because of the fact that
 males dominate the power structure, women may not be allowed to achieve their
 potential.  If a woman objectifies a man, it does not carry over into the
 education system, the workplace, the society in general as much as the reverse
 case. 

EXHIBIT B

Poetry Conference, Item 22

This is an item entered in the Poetry conference in February 1999. It is available on the Internet at http://www.cyberspace.org/cgi-bin/backtalk/peek:poetry3:22.

Item #22 entered by zoe frost (zoe) on Thu Feb  4 19:34:22 1999
 a haunting past....

 "now take this.."
 pushed to the ground,
 crushed by 190 pounds of sheer anger...
 held down--
 helpless and small...
 "now you'll get what you want,"
 "i know exactly what you want.."
 screaming gives me bruises,
 crying gets me a broken nose...
 never ending--
 thrusts,
 painful motions,
 being driven into the dirt...
 "this is what you like, isn't it?"
 "you think you're so perfect, well i don't see it.."
 whimpering under my breath..
 is this what i'm here for...
 please let this end,
 please let it go away...
 i slash his face
 "YOU MONSTER!!"
 a blade to my throat..
 heavy breathing--
 i have stirred the demons within him a little too much..
 "you fucking whore.."
 "you fucking bitch!!!"
 thrown head-first into a cold brick wall,
 unconcious and left for dead...
 take away this horror--
 let me live as i once did...
 make his aweful face disappear from my nightmares...
 let me be whole again.

27 responses total.

#1 zoe frost (zoe) on Thu Feb  4 19:40:24 1999:
 i thought i'd feel better after i posted this... i've had this in my
 head for too long, its about time i let go and try to go back to life..
 i don't know... it's not very poetic, but its been eating away at my
 soul, one of the many monsters inside me that i needed to expose.. and
 joe, i told you it wasn't pleasant so don't be all weird with me.

#2 Julie Pratt (bookworm) on Thu Feb  4 23:48:58 1999:
 Good heavens, Zoe.  This poem is very emotional.  Obviously, you and Joe
 are poets of the same school.  Did posting this help you feel better?

#3 Joe Parish (toking) on Fri Feb  5 05:44:01 1999:
 ....
 define wierd

 I think mayhap we should discuss this, elsewhere, but we should discuss
 this.

#4 Jon the Arborean (lumen) on Fri Feb  5 18:42:58 1999:
 Saints have mercy.  I hope this isn't real-life inspired?

 you may reply privately by e-mail, if you wish..my direct address is in
 my .plan file.

 Good heavens, this is creepy.  Zoe, I hope you do know that we care
 here, and we are supportive if you are writing about real life events.
 (Poetry can be very theraputic.)

#5 speaking (cloud) on Fri Feb  5 20:06:07 1999:
 On the other hand, if everyone is falling into the trap of Biographical
 >Fallicy, than you have my permission, as mr. Mannors, to tell 'em to shove
 >off.  Actually, you have my permission to anyway.
 >
 >Guys, can you please focus on the poem alone and try not to read into the
 >author's life from it?  It can be rather damaging, in my oh so humble
 >opinion.  See, I'll sometimes post something that is _partially_ based on
 real
 >life, partially not.  If someone starts speculating that the peice in
 question
 >is really about me, I tend to be embarressed into not entering new items.

 And yes, I have read the poem.  Generally speaking I, too, find it very
 disconcerting, owing to the strong language, intense pace, and taboo- nay,
 shocking,- subject matter.  I can't honestly say I like it, but I get the
 feeling that this isn't a piece to be liked, if you see my point.

#6 zoe frost (zoe) on Sat Feb  6 23:20:07 1999:
 life is pain...

#7 EA Poe (logansan) on Sun Feb  7 16:58:00 1999:
        My fellow poet/artist .... I offer you what ever little comfort I
 might. my best wishes and toughts. There is more to life than pain. Your words
 have done so much for me, even this peice of raw force, blunt trama .... it's
 taken me close to two days to get back here to make a 'r'.
        You are one of the best, zoe frost, I salute you.
                                signed; John

#8 speaking (cloud) on Sun Feb  7 19:02:31 1999:
 re:6

 "Anyone who tells you differently is trying to sell you something," eh?

#9 Julie Pratt (bookworm) on Sun Feb  7 19:36:28 1999:
 Amen. <removes her hat>  A moment of silence in memory of the loss of
 our innocence, please.

#10 zoe frost (zoe) on Mon Feb  8 10:14:56 1999:
 i hope you all realize that i'm afraid to post stuff now, since you
 have high expectations....

#11 Paul Kershaw (brighn) on Mon Feb  8 10:54:48 1999:
 Pain is pain.
 Life is life.
 Life has pain.
 Pain has life.
 Life is not pain.
 Pain is not life.

 And when my innocence died, I lit a bonfire and had a party.
 Innocence ain't anything like what it's cracked up to be.

#12 zoe frost (zoe) on Mon Feb  8 11:05:01 1999:
 it matters who's life you're living i supose...

#13 Allida (allida) on Mon Feb  8 14:30:46 1999:
 no it only matters how one perceives one's life as to whether it is indeed
 pain instead of just having pain in it. 

#14 Julie Pratt (bookworm) on Mon Feb  8 14:36:14 1999:
 Don't let the criticism of the masses stop you from posting, Zoe.  Take
 it as constructive or, if you don't like it, ignore it. 

 On the other hand, you don't have to post if you don't want to. 
 However, we'll be less for it because we won't have your brilliant
 poetry to read anymore.

 Is that as clear as mud?

#15 Jon the Arborean (lumen) on Mon Feb  8 17:31:08 1999:
 re: resp:5  Please do not take what I said the wrong way; when I read a
 very disturbing poem, I tend to take it very seriously unless the author
 says that he/she is detached from the poem in some way.

 Joe posted a story once where the main character killed a hitchhiker in
 cold blood.  He explained he had absolutely no experience in killing.

 I frequently use poetry to express my fears, frustrations, and various
 moods, mixed as they sometimes can be from time to time.  I've also been
 in therapy for a long time, long enough that I take notice when someone
 posts something melancholy.

 Zoe, please don't think I criticized you-- from the most bitter trials
 and hardship come the sweetest fruits.  Sometimes, rose bushes won't
 grow well unless you dig the whole sucker up, turn it 180 degrees, and
 replant it.  Please do not think that we expect differently from you. 
 We have been very impressed, and no one would think less of you if you
 didn't always write your best poetry.

#16 zoe frost (zoe) on Mon Feb  8 19:03:19 1999:
 i didn't take anything personally.. fear not, for i'd rather spend all
 day on the poetry confrence <<like i did today>> than anything else..
 citisim or not..
 this was just a painful thought that i've been holding since childhood
 that i needed to share.. it wasn't to be liked... it was like life;
 cold, harsh facts dished out for the sake of itself.

#17 Joe Parish (toking) on Tue Feb  9 12:12:18 1999:
 "it was like life;
  cold, harsh facts dished out for the sake of itself. "

 If I ever write a book, I'm stealing this line and using it as the firs
 and last in the book.

#18 zoe frost (zoe) on Tue Feb  9 14:45:18 1999:
 i'm honored you see so much in my words..

#19 Julie Pratt (bookworm) on Wed Feb 10 00:46:43 1999:
 we *All* see a lot in your words.

#20 Paul Kershaw (brighn) on Wed Feb 10 10:52:48 1999:
 don't speak for all of us, Julie

#21 Jon the Arborean (lumen) on Thu Feb 11 01:31:15 1999:
 why-- you don't agree, Paul?

 I can see why Joe wants to steal that line-- it's very eloquent.

#22 Paul Kershaw (brighn) on Thu Feb 11 17:38:37 1999:
 I don't like being spoken for, Jon.
 Beyond that, I'm not going to comment.

#23 Jon the Arborean (lumen) on Fri Feb 12 14:43:30 1999:
 s'ok, Paul, I understand-- I was just curious.  As for Julie, she likes
 to sound as supportive as she can.

#24 Joe Parish (toking) on Wed Feb 17 13:37:22 1999:
 (linked to the new poetry conf)

#25 Julie the Arborean (bookworm) on Mon Feb 22 02:28:47 1999:
 okay, okay. 

 I apologize, Paul.

 It wasn't my intention to be offensive.

 Still, *don't* you find meaning in her words?

#26 Paul Kershaw (brighn) on Mon Feb 22 12:37:08 1999:
 I don't think it's fair to ask qa question that I've already strongly implied
 I don't wish to answer publicly.

#27 Julie Pratt (bookworm) on Mon Feb 22 16:57:52 1999:
 okay. 
 Sorry for pushing.

UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT
EASTERN DISTRICT OF MICHIGAN
SOUTHERN DIVISION

Cyberspace, Communications, Inc.,
Arbornet, Marty Klein, Aids Partnership
of Michigan, Art on The Net, Mark
Amerika of Alt-X, Web Del Sol, Glad
Day Bookshop, Inc., Litline, American
Civil Liberties Union,

Plaintiffs,

v. |   | No. 99-cv-73150
Hon. Arthur J. Tarnow
John Engler, Governor of the State of
Michigan, and Jennifer M. Granholm,
Attorney General of the State of Michigan,

Defendants.

_________________________/ |

FINDINGS OF FACT AND CONCLUSIONS OF LAW
REGARDING PLAINTIFFS' MOTION FOR INJUNCTIVE RELIEF [1]

In 1978, the Michigan Legislature enacted a statute to protect children by prohibiting the distribution of obscene materials to children of this state. 1978 Public Act 33, M.C.L. 722.671 et seq.; M.S.A. 25.254(1) et. seq. In an effort to modernize the statute in light of current technology (and in an effort to make other improvements in the operation of the statute), the Legislature amended the statute by means of 1999 Public Act 33 (hereinafter referred to as the "Act"). The Act primarily attempts to do two things: 1) it adds criminal prohibitions against using computers or the Internet to disseminate sexually explicit materials to minors, and, 2) it changed the language of the statute so that the statute prohibits the dissemination of "sexually explicit" materials to minors rather than "obscene" materials.

The Act, amendments to M.C.L. 722.671 et seq., was signed by Defendant, John Engler, the Governor of Michigan on June 1, 1999. It is set to take effect August 1, 1999. Plaintiffs represent a broad spectrum of organizations and individuals who use the Internet to communicate, disseminate, display and access a broad range of speech and ideas. Plaintiffs include speakers, content providers, and/or Internet service providers (ISPs).

Plaintiffs claim that the Act will adversely impact them because it is unconstitutionally vague or overbroad. They maintain it will have a chilling effect on their freedom of speech under the First Amendment. Plaintiffs communicate online both within and outside of the state of Michigan. Their speech is accessible within and outside of the state of Michigan. For this reason, Plaintiffs further argue that the Act violates the Commerce Clause of the United States Constitution. They have requested this Court issue a preliminary injunction to enjoin the amendments to the statute.

I. The Amended Statute
The central prohibition contained in the amended act is found in M.C.L. 722.675(1); M.S.A. 25.254(5)(1):

A person is guilty of disseminating sexually explicit matter to a minor if that person does either of the following:

(a) Knowingly disseminates to a minor sexually explicit visual or verbal material that is harmful to minors;

(b) Knowingly exhibits to a minor a sexually explicit performance that is harmful to minors.

The Act redefines obscenity as "sexually explicit matter"[2] . The Act makes it unlawful to communicate, transmit, display, or otherwise make available by means of the Internet or a computer, computer program, computer system, or computer network this sexually explicit matter. M.C.L. 722.673; M.S.A. 25.254(3). Violation of the statute is a felony punishable by up to two years in prison and a fine of $10,000. 722.675(5); M.S.A. 25.254(5)(5)[3]. Finally, the Act threatens criminal sanctions "if the violation originates, terminates, or both originates and terminates" in the State of Michigan. (M.C.L. 722.675(8), M.S.A. 25.254(5)(8)).

The 1999 P.A. 33 amendments were specifically intended to apply the pre-existing statute's prohibition on the dissemination of sexually explicit matter to communication over the Internet. Because of the anonymous and borderless nature of the Internet, Plaintiffs fear the amendments will subject them to criminal prosecution for the expression of protected speech. They filed suit challenging the Act. Plaintiffs then asked to enjoin the Act's enforcement scheduled to begin August 1, 1999.

A hearing was held on the Motion for a Preliminary Injunction on July 22, 1999. The Court wishes to thank the parties for the thoroughness and quality of the arguments presented.

The following constitutes the Court's findings of fact and conclusions of law:

II. The Internet

Based on the testimony presented at the hearing on the preliminary injunction motion, based on the parties' stipulation of facts, and based on the factual findings of other federal courts, including the United States Supreme Court,[4] the Court finds the following to accurately describe the Internet:

The Nature of the Internet

1. The Internet is a decentralized, global communications medium that links people, institutions, corporations and governments around the world. ACLU, 929 F. Supp. at 831; Pataki, 969 F. Supp at 164; Johnson, 4 F. Supp. 2d at 1031.

2. The Internet is a giant computer "network of networks" which interconnects innumerable smaller groups of linked computer networks and individual computers offering a range of digital information including text, images, sound and video, . Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2334; Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 164; Johnson, 4 F. Supp. 2d at 1031; Reno II, 31 F. Supp. 2d at 481.

3. While estimates are difficult due to its constant and rapid growth, the Internet is currently believed to connect more than 159 countries, and over 100 million users. ACLU v. Reno, 929 F. Supp. at 831; Johnson, 4 F. Supp. 2d at 1031. The amount of traffic on the Internet is doubling approximately every 100 days.

4. Content ranges from academic writings, to art, to humor, to literature, to medical information, to music, to news, to sexually oriented material. Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 164; Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2335.

5. Sexually explicit material is available on the Internet; however, it is not "the primary type of content on this new medium." ACLU v. Reno, 929 F. Supp. at 844; Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 164; Reno II, 31 F. Supp. 2d at 484.

6. In addition, at any one time, the Internet serves as the communication medium for tens of thousands of global conversations, political debates, and social dialogues. Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 165-166.

7. The Internet is distinguishable in important ways from traditional media. It is a revolutionary medium that is dramatically altering traditional views of communications and community, See ACLU v. Reno, 929 F. Supp. at 843-844. No single organization controls any membership in the Web, nor is there any centralized point from which individual Web sites or services can be blocked. Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2336; Reno II, 31 F. Supp. 2d at 484.

8. The Internet is a global medium. Reno II, 31 F. Supp. 2d at 482. At least 40% of the content of the Internet originates abroad. Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2334; Reno II, 31 F. Supp. 2d at 484.

9. The Internet also differs from traditional media in that it provides users with an ability to interact with other users and with content. ACLU v. Reno, 929 F. Supp. at 843-44. Unlike radio or television, communications on the Internet do not "invade" an individual's home or appear on one's computer screen unbidden. Id. at 844. Rather, the receipt of information on the Internet "requires a series of affirmative steps more deliberate and directed than merely turning a dial." Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2336 (quoting ACLU v. Reno, 929 F. Supp. at 845).

10. Because the Internet presents extremely low entry barriers to publishers and distributors of information, it is an especially attractive method of communicating for non-profit and public interest groups. ACLU v. Reno, 929 F. Supp. at 843; Reno II, 31 F. Supp. 2d at 482.

11. Any person or organization with a computer connected to the Internet can "publish" information. Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2335.

12. Also, unlike radio, television, newspapers and books, the Internet is not exclusively, or even primarily, a means of commercial communication. Reno v. ACLU, 929 F. Supp. at 842. In sum, the Internet is "a unique and wholly new medium of worldwide human communication." Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2334 (quoting ACLU v. Reno, 929 F. Supp. at 844).

How Individuals Access the Internet

13. Individuals may obtain easy access to the Internet in particular through many educational institutions, businesses, libraries, and individual communities who maintain computer networks linked directly to the Internet and provide account numbers and passwords enabling users to gain access to the network. Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2334; Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 164-165.

14. Internet service providers ("ISPs"), such as plaintiffs Cyberspace Communications and Arbornet.org, offer their subscribers modem access to computers or networks maintained by the ISP which are linked directly to the Internet. ACLU v. Reno, 929 F. Supp. at 832-33; Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2334; Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 165; Reno II, 31 F. Supp. 2d at 482.

Ways of Communicating and Exchanging Information on the Internet

15. Most users of the Internet are provided with a username, password and electronic mail (or "e-mail") address that allow them to sign on to the Internet and to communicate with other users. Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 165.

16. Many usernames are pseudonyms or pen names that often provide users with a distinct online identity and help to preserve their anonymity. An e-mail sender directs his or her message to a "logical rather than geographic address." Id.

17. The username and e-mail address are the only indicators of the user's identity. Persons communicating with the user will know them only by their username and e-mail address (unless the user reveals other information about herself through her messages). Id. Anonymity of the communicant is both important and valuable to the free exchange of ideas and information on the Internet.

18. Once an individual signs on to the Internet, there are a wide variety of methods for communicating and exchanging information with other users. See generally Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2334-35; ACLU v. Reno, 929 F. Supp. at 834-38; Shea, 930 F. Supp. at 927-30; Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 165; Reno II, 31 F. Supp. 2d at 482-483. The primary methods are:

E-Mail:
"E-mail enables an individual to send an electronic message - generally akin to a note or letter - to another individual or to a group of addresses." Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2335; Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 165.
Online Discussion Groups:
Thousands of discussion groups have been organized by individuals, institutions, and organizations on many different computer networks and cover virtually every topic imaginable -- creating a new, global version of the village green. The three most common methods for online discussion are mail exploders, USENET newsgroups, and chat rooms.
Mail Exploders:
Mail exploders, also called mailing lists, allow online users to subscribe to automated mailing lists that disseminate information on particular subjects. Subscribers send an e-mail message to the "list," and the mail exploder automatically and simultaneously sends the message to all of the other subscribers on the list. Subscribers can reply to the message by sending a response to the list. Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2335. Users of mailing lists typically can add or remove their names from the list automatically, with no direct human involvement. ACLU v. Reno, 929 F. Supp. at 834; Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 165-166.
USENET Newsgroups:
"USENET" newsgroups are a popular set of discussion groups arranged according to subject matter and automatically disseminated "using ad hoc, peer to peer connections between approximately 200,000 computers . . . around the world." Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2335 (quoting ACLU v. Reno, 929 F. Supp. at 834-35); see also Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 166. Users may read or send messages to most newsgroups without a prior "subscription," and there is no way for a speaker who posts an article to most newsgroups to know who is reading her message. Id.
Chat Rooms:
"Chat rooms" provide additional online discussion forums that allow users to engage in real time dialogue with one or many other users by typing messages and reading the messages typed by others participating in the chat, analogous to a telephone party line, using a computer and keyboard rather than a telephone. Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2335; ACLU v. Reno, 929 F. Supp. at 835. There are thousands of different chat rooms available "in which collectively tens of thousands of users are engaging in conversations on a huge range of subjects." Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2335 (quoting ACLU v. Reno, 929 F. Supp. at 835); Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 166.
The World Wide Web:
The Web allows users to publish documents, also called "Web pages," that can then be accessed by any other user in the world. See generally Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2335, and 929 F. Supp. at 836-38; Shea, 930 F. Supp. at 929-30; Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 166; Reno II, 31 F. Supp. 2d at 484. The Web comprises millions of separate "Web sites" that display content provided by particular persons or organizations. Any Internet user anywhere in the world with the proper software can create her own Web page, view Web pages posted by others, and then read text, look at images and video, and listen to sounds posted at these sites. Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 166. There are Web sites now by large corporations, banks, brokerage houses, newspapers and magazines, and government agencies and courts. Id.

19. There are a number of different ways that Internet users can browse or search for content on the Web: by specific address ("URL") or by "search engines," which are available free of charge to help users navigate the Web, Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2335; Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 166; or by "linking" from one Web page to another. Reno II, 31 F. Supp. 2d at 483. Almost all Web documents contain "links," which are short sections of text or image that refer and link to another Web document. Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2335; Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 166-167; Reno II, 31 F. Supp. 2d at 484. When selected by the user, the "linked" document is automatically displayed, wherever in the world it is actually stored. Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2335; Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 166; Reno II, 31 F. Supp. 2d at 484. "The Web is thus comparable . . . to both a vast library including millions of readily available and indexed publications and a sprawling mall offering goods and services." Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2335.

20. "Taken together, these tools constitute a unique medium - known to its users as `cyberspace' - located in no particular geographical location but available to anyone, anywhere in the world, with access to the Internet." Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2334-35.

21. Once a provider posts content on the Internet, it is available to most other Internet users worldwide. ACLU v. Reno, 929 F. Supp. at 844; Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 167; Johnson, 4 F. Supp. 2d at 1032.

22. For the vast majority of communications over the Internet, including all communications over the Web, by e-mail, newsgroups, mail exploders, and chat rooms, it is not technologically possible for a speaker to determine the age of a user who is accessing such communications. See Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2336-37 (quoting ACLU v. Reno, 929 F. Supp. at 845) ("There is no effective way to determine the identity or the age of a user who is accessing material through e-mail, mail exploders, newsgroups, or chat rooms."); Shea, 930 F. Supp. at 941 ("for the vast majority of applications and services available on the Internet, a user has no way of communicating . . . with certainty that the content will not reach a person under eighteen . . . ."); Reno II, 31 F. Supp. 2d at 495 ("the nature of the Web and the Internet is such that Web site operators and content providers cannot know who is accessing their sites, or from where, or how old the users are, unless they take affirmative steps to gather information from the user, and the user is willing to give them truthful responses.").

Thus, these categories of speakers either must make their information available to all users of the Internet, including users who may be minors, or not make it available at all. This is also true for non-Web-based communications by e-mail, newsgroups, mail exploders, and chat rooms.

For Web speakers, the vast majority cannot now determine the age of people accessing their speech and many could not technologically change their site even to request information on age. Also, even for those Web sites, or other Internet speakers, who ask readers to state their age, there is no reasonable method by which the speaker can determine the reliability of that information.

The Availability of User-Based Filtering Programs

24. There are a variety of options available to parents and other users who wish to restrict access to online communications that they might consider unsuitable for minors. See generally Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2337, and ACLU v. Reno, 929 F. Supp. at 838-42; Shea, 930 F. Supp. at 931-34.

25. First, there are a variety of user-based software products that allow users to block access to sexually explicit materials on the Web, to prevent minors from giving personal information to strangers by e-mail or in chat rooms, and to keep a log of all online activity that occurs on the home computer. Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2337. "The market for this type of [user-based] software is growing, and there is increasing competition among software providers to provide products." ACLU v. Reno, 929 F. Supp. at 839.

26. Second, large commercial online services such as America Online provide features to prevent minors from accessing chat rooms and to block access to certain newsgroups based on keywords, subject matter, or specific newsgroup. Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2336; Johnson, 4 F. Supp. 2d at 1033; Reno II, 31 F. Supp. 2d at 492.

27. Third, the large online services such as America Online also offer parental control options free of charge to their members. America Online has established an online area designed specifically for children. The "Kids Only" parental control feature allows parents to establish an America Online account for their children that accesses only the "Kids Only" channel on America Online. ACLU v. Reno, 929 F. Supp. at 842.

The Interstate Nature of Online Communication

28. The Internet is wholly insensitive to geographic distinctions, and Internet protocols were designed to ignore rather than document geographic location. Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 167, 170; Johnson, 4 F. Supp. 2d at 1032.

29. While computers on the network do have "addresses," they are digital addresses on the network rather than geographic addresses in real space. The majority of Internet addresses contain no geographic indicators. Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 170.

30. Like the nation's railways and highways, the Internet is by nature an instrument of interstate commerce. Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 173; Johnson, 4 F. Supp. 2d at 1032. Just as goods and services travel over state borders by truck and train, information flows freely across state borders on the Internet. Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 173.

31. It is this characteristic which has earned the Internet the nickname, "the information superhighway." Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 161.

32. In fact, no aspect of the Internet can feasiblely be closed to users from another state. Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 171; Johnson, 4 F. Supp. 2d at 1032. There is no way to stop or bar speech at Michigan's border.

33. An Internet user who posts a Web page cannot prevent Michiganians or Oklahomans or Iowans from accessing that page. They will not even know the state residency of any visitors to that site, unless the information is voluntarily (and accurately) given by the visitor. Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 171; Reno II, 31 F. Supp. 2d at 495; Johnson, 4 F. Supp. 2d at 1032.

34. Participants in chat rooms and online discussion groups also have no way of knowing when participants from a particular state have joined the conversation. Id; Johnson, 4 F. Supp. 2d at 1032.

35. Because most e-mail accounts allow users to download their mail from anywhere, it is impossible for someone who sends an e-mail to know with certainty where the recipient is located geographically. Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 171.

36. In addition, the Internet is a redundant series of linked computers over which information often travels randomly. Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 164, 171. Thus, a message from an Internet user sitting at a computer in New York may travel via one or more other states - including Michigan - before reaching a recipient who is also sitting at a computer in New York. Id; Johnson, 4 F. Supp. 2d at 1032.

37. There is no way for an Internet user to prevent his or her message from reaching residents of any particular state. Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 171; Johnson, 4 F. Supp. 2d at 1032. Similarly, "[o]nce a provider posts its content on the Internet, it cannot prevent that content from entering any community." Reno I, 117 S. Ct. at 2336 (quoting ACLU v. Reno, 929 F. Supp. at 844).

III. Standing

Defendants argue that the threshold issue before the court is that the Plaintiffs lack standing to bring this request for injunctive relief. A plaintiff must have standing to bring or pursue a claim in federal court. Arizonans for Official English v Arizona, 520 U.S. 43, 117 S.Ct. 1055, 137 L.Ed.2d 170 (1997). Standing is a question of judicial power, and it is the threshold question in every federal case. Warth v Seldin, 422 U.S. 490, 95 S. Ct. 2205, 45 L.Ed.2d 343 (1975). Standing encompasses at least three factors:

an injury in fact - i.e., an injury which is concrete and actual or imminent, not merely speculative or hypothetical;
a causal relationship between the injury and the challenged conduct; and
a likelihood that the injury will be redressed by a favorable decision.

Lujan v Defenders of Wildlife, 504 U.S. 555, 112 S.Ct. 2130, L.Ed.2d 351 (1992). "Although `imminence' is concededly a somewhat elastic concept, it cannot be stretched beyond its purpose, which is to ensure that the alleged injury is not too speculative for Article III purposes - that the injury is `certainly impending'." Id. at 564, n.2, 112 S.Ct. at 2138, n. 2. (Emphasis in original).

Defendants claim that to address these issues raised by plaintiffs is to issue an advisory opinion because the statute is yet to go into effect and Plaintiffs have not yet been injured in fact.[5]

Under the criteria outlined by the Supreme Court in Lujan, the plaintiffs have standing, because an alleged injury is `certainly impending', if the statute takes effect and the material they disseminate is deemed "sexually explicit". No one should have to go through being arrested for a felony, publically shamed, and pay for a defense only to have a court find that the newly enacted statute is unconstitutional. This can, and should, be determined before such injury occurs. Such a challenge can be brought by those that may be accused, or injured in fact, by such a statute.

Plaintiffs include:

Cyberspace Communications ("Cyberspace") is a tax exempt Michigan non-profit corporation. Cyberspace maintains a free public access Internet service called "Grex," at the Internet address: Cyberspace.org. Currently approximately 29,000 users access Grex through the World Wide Web or through a bank of dial-in modems located in Ann Arbor, Michigan.
Arbornet is a tax-exempt Michigan non-profit corporation. Arbornet runs M-Net, "America's first public access Unix system." M-Net began operations on June 16, 1983. Arbornet's users obtain services such as conferences, e-mail, chat, and Internet access, generally at no cost.
Marty Klein is a licensed Marriage and Family Therapist in Palo Alto, California. In addition to his practice as a therapist working with individuals and couples, Dr. Klein is also the author of numerous books and articles about human sexuality. Dr. Klein has maintained a Web site, located at www.Sexed.org.
Aids Partnership of Michigan ("Aids Partnership") maintains a Web site, at the address www.aidspartnership.org, which contains information regarding HIV and Aids, including the most recent scientifically available facts about the methods of transmitting HIV and testing for HIV and Aids, and methods of safer sex practices.
Art on the Net is a non-profit organization with an international artist site ("art.net") on the Web. Art on the Net assists over 125 artists from all over the world in maintaining online studios.
Mark Amerika is a critically acclaimed writer and publisher of Alt-X, a Web site containing original literary works published only online, reviews of new media art and theory, original online art projects. Alt-X has been called "the literary publishing model of the future."
Web Del Sol is a voluntary association which functions as a dynamic, literary arts complex on the Internet. Its Web address is www.webdelsol.com. Web Del Sol was founded as a forum for the collaborative literary efforts of dozens of editors and writers, and hosts a vast array of poems, articles, essays, and photography, as well as a bulletin board and a chat room.
Glad Day Bookshop is a bookstore located in Boston, Massachusetts, that specializes in gay and lesbian books and also maintains a Web site on which visitors may obtain information about Glad Day Bookshop and the books it makes available. Its Web site is located at www.tiac.net/users/gladday.
Litline a nonprofit web site set up by the Counsel for Literary Magazines and Presses (CLMP) to provide Internet content for independent literary presses, journals, and organizations. Its Web address is www.litline.org. Litline mainly provides free design and hosting services to eleven independent literary journals and six independent presses, none of which could otherwise afford to go online.
American Civil Liberties Union ("ACLU") is a national civil rights organization. The ACLU maintains a Web site on which it posts civil liberties information and resources, including material about arts censorship, obscenity laws, discrimination against lesbians and gays, and reproductive choice. In addition, the ACLU hosts unmoderated online discussion groups that allow citizens to discuss and debate a variety of civil liberties issues.

All the Plaintiffs justifiably fear prosecution. They have stated that they disseminate on the Internet sexually explicit material which arguably could be deemed "harmful to minors". Absent an injunction they must self-censor their speech on the Internet or else risk prosecution under the Act. These allegations of harm are sufficient to confer standing in this action for declaratory and injunctive relief. "In the context of threats to the right of free expression," it is not necessary "that an individual first be exposed to prosecution in order to have standing to challenge a statute which is claimed to deter the exercise of constitutional rights." Briggs v. Ohio Elections Comm'n, 61 F.3d 487, 492 (6 th Cir. 1995) (citations omitted). These allegations of harm also sufficiently support a request for a preliminary injunction. G & V Lounge, Inc. v. Michigan Liquor Control Comm'n, 23 F.3d 1071, 1078-79 (6 th Cir. 1994). See also Dombrowski v. Pfister, 380 U.S. 479 (1965); Steffel v. Thomspon, 415 U.S. 452 (1974). The Plaintiffs in this case have standing and are entitled to a preliminary injunction, because the Act poses a threat to their rights under the U.S. Constitution. See also, ACLU v. Johnson, 4 F. Supp. 2d at 1027; ALA v. Pataki, 969 F. Supp. 160 (S.D.N.Y. 1997).

IV. First Amendment Challenge

The First Amendment to the United States Constitution provides in pertinent part that "Congress shall make no law . . . abridging freedom of speech." The prohibitions of the First Amendment extend to the several States through the Fourteenth Amendment.

Defendants argue Ginsberg v. New York, 390 U.S. 629, 88 S.Ct. 1274, 20 L.Ed.2d 195 (1968) and Miller v California, 413 U.S. 15, 93 S.Ct. 2607, 37 L.Ed. 2419 (1973), for the proposition that `obscenity' is not protected by the First Amendment. In Ginsberg, the Supreme Court held that a state could prohibit the dissemination to minors of sexually explicit materials which would not be legally obscene with regard to an adult. In Miller, the Supreme Court stated:

This much has been categorically settled by the Court, that obscene material is unprotected by the First Amendment. Kois v. Wisconsin, 408 U.S. 229, 92 S.Ct. 2245, 33 L.Ed.2d 312 (1972); (citations omitted).

We acknowledge, however, the inherent dangers of undertaking to regulate any form of expression. State statutes designed to regulate obscene materials must be carefully limited. See Interstate Circuit, Inc. v. Dallas, supra, 390 U.S., at 682--685, 88 S.Ct., at 1302--1305. As a result, we now confine the permissible scope of such regulation to works which depict or describe sexual conduct. That conduct must be specifically defined by the applicable state law, as written or authoritatively construed. A state offense must also be limited to works which, taken as a whole, appeal to the prurient interest in sex, which portray sexual conduct in a patently offensive way, and which, taken as a whole, do not have serious literary, artistic, political, or scientific value.

Id. at 23-24, S.Ct. at 2614-15.

Defendants argue that the Act comports to the specifications of Ginsberg and Miller; therefore, the Act is constitutional. Yet in these cases, the `materials' referenced were magazines and brochures, respectively. Magazines or brochures can be brown bagged or hidden in the backroom of purveyors. With the Internet, you would have to `close the bookstore' because the disseminator and the recipient are not face to face. A magazine can be regulated or censored by the county in which it is located. A person's age can be verified because that person is physically there, and the disseminator can logically be held responsible for conveying "sexually explicit matter" to a minor. The Internet does not distinguish between minors and adults in their audience. To comply with the Act, a communicant must speak only in language suitable for children. Even under the guise of protecting minors, the government may not justify the complete suppression of constitutionally protected speech because to do so would "burn the house to roast the pig." Butler v Michigan, 352 U.S. 380, 383, 77 S.Ct. 524, 525, 1 L.Ed.2d 412 (1957).

The Internet is cyberspace, or an international network of computers. It is virtually impossible to prevent the content of messages from being read by someone under 18. The only way to ascertain an individuals age would be to require submission of a driver's license, birth certificate or some other form of identification. Considering a website may receive ten to a million plus "hits" a day, and many of these websites are established and maintained by even just one publisher; the impossibility of identification checking is understood. With the imposition of the government policing speech and deciding what is acceptable; a user, publisher, disseminator or communicant is faced with a Hobson's choice [6] of shutting down their website (or whatever vehicle of information exchange), or risk prosecution for exercising protected speech.

The Act itself may in fact pass constitutional muster as a permitted regulation of obscenity, as it is quite similarly worded as those statutes upheld by the Supreme Court in Miller and Ginsberg. Defendant argues that a state does have the police power to regulate obscenity within their borders. This is true, but proper focus centers on this Public Act's impact on the Internet. The Internet is an international free flow of ideas and information. Enforcement of this Act would stifle one of the cornerstones of American Society - what Thomas Jefferson called "The Marketplace of Ideas."

The amended statute at issue limits the receipt and communication of information through the Internet based on the content of that information. A content-based limitation on speech will be upheld only where the state demonstrates that the limitation "is necessary to serve a compelling state interest and that it is narrowly drawn to achieve that end." Perry Educ. Ass'n. v. Perry Local Educators' Ass'n, 460 U.S. 37, 45, 103 S.Ct. 948, 74 L.Ed.2d 794 (1983) (citing Carey v. Brown, 447 U.S. 455, 461, 100 S.Ct. 2286, 65 L.Ed.2d 263 (1980)).

This test involves three distinct inquiries:[7] (1) whether the interests asserted by the state are compelling; (2) whether the limitation is necessary to further those interests; and (3) whether the limitation is narrowly drawn to achieve those interests. Mainstream Loudoun v Board of Trustees of Loudoun County Library, 24 F.Supp.2d 552, 564-65 (E.D. Va. 1998).

(1). Whether the Defendant's Interests Are Compelling

The Internet offers users quick and relatively simple access to a wide variety of information resources, products and services, and opportunities for interactive communication with millions of people through the use of a computer. . . . Despite the beneficial and education advantages of the Internet's growing network of information, the Internet is not without its problems. One common concern, particularly in light of the number of children who use the Internet, is the relative ease with which children can access materials that their parents might find offensive.

House Legislative Analysis, Senate Bill 117 (March 18, 1999)

The Court is quite sympathetic to the attempt of the Michigan legislature to protect minors. Society has a compelling interest in preserving the innocence of their children. Although Defendants have failed to address this prong, there is arguably a compelling state interest to shelter our children from sexually explicit material until maturity. The Supreme Court has recognized such an interest: "We have recognized that there is a compelling interest in protecting the physical and psychological well-being of minors. This interest extends to shielding minors from the influence of literature that is not obscene by adult standards." Sable Communications of California, Inc. v FCC, 492 U.S. 115, 126, 109 S.Ct. 2829, 2836, 106 L.Ed.2d 93 (1989), quoting Ginsberg v. New York, 390 U.S. 629, 639-640, 88 S.Ct. 1274, 1280-81, 20 L.Ed.2d 195 (1968); and New York v. Ferber, 458 U.S. 747, 756-757, 102 S.Ct. 3348, 3354-55, 73 L.Ed.2d 1113 (1982).

(2) Whether the Act is Necessary to Further Those Interests

To satisfy strict scrutiny, defendants must do more than demonstrate that it has a compelling interest; they must also demonstrate that the Act is necessary to further that interest. Defendants "must demonstrate that the recited harms are real, not merely conjectural, and that the regulation will in fact alleviate these harms in a direct and material way." Turner Broadcasting Systems, Inc. v. FCC, 512 U.S. 622, 664, 114 S.Ct. 2445, 129 L.Ed.2d 497 (1994); see also Johnson, 865 F.Supp. at 1439 ("[S]imply alleging the need to avoid sexual harassment is not enough [;] ... the defendant[ ] must show that the threat of disruption is actual, material, and substantial."). The defendant bears this burden because "[t]he interest in encouraging freedom of expression in a democratic society outweighs any theoretical but unproven benefit of censorship." Reno v. ACLU, 521 U.S. 844, 117 S.Ct. 2329, 2351, 138 L.Ed.2d 874 (1997).

The Defendants failed to satisfy that the Act will further a compelling interest of the State. Plaintiffs though did submit testimony and documentation that such an Act could produce a result contrary to the desires of society. The free flow of information on the Internet enables a teenager to ask about premarital sex or sexually transmitted diseases with anonymity. Plaintiffs at the hearing read into the record an example of a teenager asking Dr. Marty Klein, a sex therapist in California and plaintiff in this case, who operates a website entitled "Ask Me Anything", about an encounter with her boyfriend that she incorrectly reasoned was not sexual intercourse. Other examples offered at the hearing include submitted transcripts of chat room discussions concerning contraceptives and abstention. Sometimes words were utilized in these discussions which could be construed as "sexually explicit" and "harmful to a minor", which theoretically could subject the disseminator to criminal prosecution.

This would have an adverse affect on public policy. With all Internet participants fearful of criminal prosecution if certain terminology is utilized, the discussions would be stifled to the point that a teenager seeking answers to curious questions concerning a subject foremost on their mind, could not find answers via this medium. Without open discussion of how to prevent being raped or birth control or abstention, there would quite possibly be greater numbers of teenage pregnancy or sexually transmitted diseases. This would be contrary to the interests of the State.

(3) Whether the Act Is Narrowly Tailored to Achieve the Compelling Government Interests.

Even if defendants could demonstrate that the Act was reasonably necessary to further compelling state interests, it would still have to show that the Act is narrowly tailored to achieve those interests. The government may effectuate even a compelling interest only "by narrowly drawn regulations designed to serve those interests without unnecessarily interfering with First Amendment freedoms." Sable, 492 U.S. at 126, 109 S.Ct. at 2836. The government must "choose[s] the least restrictive means to further the articulated interest." Id.

Whether Less Restrictive Means Are Available

In Sable, the Court declared unconstitutional a statute banning all "indecent" commercial telephone communications. The Court found that the government could not justify a total ban on communication that is harmful to minors, but not obscene, by arguing that only a total ban could completely prevent children from accessing indecent messages. Id. at 128, 109 S.Ct. 2829. The Court held that without evidence that less restrictive means had "been tested over time," the government had not carried its burden of proving that they would not be sufficiently effective. Id. at 128-29, 109 S.Ct. 2829.

Testimony was offered by Plaintiffs through a qualified Internet expert. Dr. Lorrie Faith Cranor is Senior Technical Staff Member for Secure Systems Research for AT&T Labs-Research in Florham Park, New Jersey. She testified at the hearing that there are many less intrusive, more effective ways to screen harmful material to minors. Some of the ways or methods that this can be accomplished is through the use of currently marketed software that restrict content received. This safe and child-friendly software works off of either a `white list' or a `black list' theory. A white list enables a parent to program what areas of the Internet their child will be allowed to enter. A black list prevents a child from venturing into certain pre-programed areas. Dr. Cranor explained that there is software available to allow parents to filter certain words that may be offensive. Some of these are smart programs that read the context in which the word is presented, e.g. differentiating between a woman's thigh and a chicken thigh. All of these software programs have settings that allow a parent to expand vocabulary words as a child matures. These programs are reasonably priced, usually between $20 to $30.

Many Internet Service Providers (ISPs) allow parents to regulate content with different levels of restriction. The ISP allows parents to establish separate accounts for their children depending on their ages restricting entry to only child-friendly, fun and educational places on the Internet. These areas are usually monitored by employees of the ISP and a communicant that shares offensive language will be blocked when discovered.

It was also noted at the hearing that Internet users have an unwritten code of decency and curiosity. If a communicant is being offensive to other chat room participants, (s)he will be told to stop. If the communicant persists, the offensive communicant will be `flamed' by the group. A flame is a continuous barrage of warnings from others. The warnings can be so continuous and overwhelming that flaming can render the black-listed recipient's computer unusable online [8] .

Dr. Cranor began her list of available methods or ways for which a parent can monitor the content of material to which a child receives, as having a parent sit down and explore with the child. Parental control is the most effective method in overseeing where the child ventures. This can be as simple as placing the computer in a common area of your home, like the living room, so the child can anticipate the presence of an adult. She suggested not placing the computer in the children's bedroom where they have the seclusion for unbounded exploration. A parent could also place a lock on the computer until such time as a parent can supervise the child. If the parent cannot directly supervise the child's computer usage, then set limits, much like what shows a child can and cannot watch on television. There are software programs that log all the websites so that a parent can have a record and the child knows that they have to adhere to limits. Finally, the Court takes judicial notice of the fact that every computer is equipped with an on/off switch.

The Court finds that the Act is not narrowly tailored, because less restrictive means are available to further Defendants' interests. As in Sable, there is no evidence that Defendants has tested any of these means over time.

In summary, Defendants have asserted a broad right to censor the expressive activity of the receipt and communication of information through the Internet with an Act that (1) addresses a compelling government interest but is not necessary to further that interest ; (2) is not narrowly tailored; and, (3) fails to employ the least restrictive means available to further that interest. The Act offends the guarantee of free speech in the First Amendment and is, therefore, unconstitutional.

V. Violation of the Commerce Clause

The Commerce Clause, U.S. Const. Art. I, Sec. 8, cl. 3, contains an express authorization for Congress to "regulate Commerce with foreign Nations, and among the several States ...". A "dormant" or "negative" aspect of this grant of power is that a state's power to impinge on interstate commerce may be limited in some situations. Quill Corp. v. North Dakota, 504 U.S. 298, 112 S.Ct. 1904, 119 L.Ed.2d 91 (1992).

Defendants do not dispute that the Act reaches interstate commerce. Rather, they contend that the Act does not discriminate against out-of-state businesses in favor of Michigan businesses. Further, the government argues, any balancing of burdens on interstate commerce with local interests must tip in favor of the local interests asserted in the Act. These contentions fail for the reasons explained in ACLU v. Pataki, 969 F. Supp. 160 (S.D.N.Y. 1997).

First, Defendants focus solely on the line of cases which prohibit a state's discrimination against out-of-state businesses. The Commerce Clause reaches further than such discrimination alone. The Commerce Clause also operates to preclude "the application of a state statute to commerce that takes place wholly outside the State's borders, whether or not the commerce has effects within the state." Pataki, 160 F. Supp. at 175 (quoting Healy v. The Beer Institute, 491 U.S. 324, 336 (1989)). Although the Act by its terms regulates speech that "originates" or "terminates" in Michigan, virtually all Internet speech is, as stipulated by Defendants available everywhere including Michigan. A New York speaker must comply with the Act in order to avoid the risk of prosecution in Michigan even though (s)he does not intend his message to be read in Michigan. A publisher of a web page cannot limit the viewing of his site to everyone in the country except for those in Michigan. The Internet has no geographic boundaries. The Act is, as a direct regulation of interstate commerce, a per se violation of the Commerce Clause.

Moreover, even if this Court reaches the balancing of burdens on interstate commerce with local interests asserted in the Act, the Commerce Clause still requires the injunction of this Act. Assuming arguendo the validity of Michigan's interest in the Act, the Act will be wholly ineffective in achieving the asserted goal because nearly half of all Internet communications originate overseas. Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 177. Just as in Martin-Marietta Corp. v. Bendix Corp., 690 F.2d 558, 566 (6 th Cir. 1982), where the Sixth Circuit said: "[W]hile protecting local investors is plainly a legitimate state objective, the state has no legitimate interest in protecting non-resident shareholders"; so to Michigan has no interest in regulating out-of-state communications.

As further explained in Pataki, the chilling effect on Internet communications outside of Michigan greatly outweighs any putative benefit inside Michigan. The Act, and other state statutes like it, would subject the Internet to inconsistent regulations across the nation. Information is a commodity and must flow freely. On this basis alone, the Act may be preliminarily enjoined as a violation of the Commerce Clause.

VI. Fundamental Right of Child Rearing

Although Plaintiffs did not raise the argument that parents have a liberty interest in how their own children are raised[9], nor is the Court's decision today based on that sound principal, the Court believes that there is a good argument to be considered.

As Mr. Justice Harlan wrote, dissenting in Poe v. Ullman, 367 U.S. 497, 551-552, 81 S.Ct. 1752, 1781, 6 L.Ed.2d 989 (1961):

(H)ere we have not an intrusion into the home so much as on the life which characteristically has its place in the home. . . . The home derives its pre-eminence as the seat of family life. And the integrity of that life is something so fundamental that it has been found to draw to its protection the principles of more than one explicitly granted Constitutional right.

* * * *

. . . (T)he full scope of the liberty guaranteed by the Due Process Clause cannot be found in or limited by the precise terms of the specific guarantees elsewhere provided in the Constitution. This 'liberty' is not a series of isolated points pricked out in terms of the taking of property; the freedom of speech, press, and religion; the right to keep and bear arms; the freedom from unreasonable searches and seizures; and so on. It is a rational continuum which, broadly speaking, includes a freedom from all substantial arbitrary impositions and purposeless restraints, . . . and which also recognizes, what a reasonable and sensitive judgment must, that certain interests require particularly careful scrutiny of the state needs asserted to justify their abridgment.

Id. at 542-543, 81 S.Ct., at 1776-1777.

Further, the Supreme Court explained in Moore v City of Cleveland, Ohio, 431 U.S. 494, 97 S. Ct. 1932, 52 L.Ed.2d 531 (1977):

But unless we close our eyes to the basic reasons why certain rights associated with the family have been accorded shelter under the Fourteenth Amendment's Due Process Clause, we cannot avoid applying the force and rationale of these precedents to the family choice involved in this case.

Id. at 502, S.Ct. at 1936.

* * * *

Our decisions establish that the Constitution protects the sanctity of the family precisely because the institution of the family is deeply rooted in this Nation's history and tradition. [footnote omitted]. It is through the family that we inculcate and pass down many of our most cherished values, moral and cultural.

Id. at 503-504, S.Ct. at 1938.

Although it is difficult in today's society to constantly monitor the activities of children, it is still the right, and duty, of every parent to teach and mold children's concepts of good and bad, right and wrong. This right is no greater than in the confines of ones own home. A family with values will supervise their children. This includes setting limits, and either being there to enforce those limits, or utilizing the available technology to do so. With such less restrictive means to monitor the online activities of children, the government need not restrict the right of free speech guaranteed to adults.

VII. Preliminary Injunction Standard

The district courts must consider the following four factors in determining whether or not to issue a preliminary injunction:

whether the movant has a "strong" likelihood of success on the merits;
whether the movant would otherwise suffer irreparable injury;
whether issuance of a preliminary injunction would cause substantial harm to others; and
whether the public interest would be served by issuance of a preliminary injunction.

McPherson v. Michigan High Sch. Athletic Ass'n, Inc., 119 F.3d 453, 459 (6th Cir.1997) (en banc) (quoting Sandison v. Michigan High Sch. Athletic Ass'n, Inc., 64 F.3d 1026, 1030 (6th Cir.1995)). These factors are not prerequisites to issuing an injunction but factors to be balanced. United Food & Commercial Workers Union Local 1099 v Southwest Ohio Regional Transit Auth., 163 F3d 341, 347 (6 th Cir. 1998).

"The purpose of a preliminary injunction is always to prevent irreparable injury so as to preserve the court's ability to render a meaningful decision on the merits." Stenberg v. Cheker Oil Co., 573 F.2d 921, 925 (6th Cir.1978); See also Canal Authority of State of Florida v. Callaway, 489 F.2d 567, 576 (5th Cir.1974) (same). Recognizing that preservation of the court's ability to exercise meaningful review may require affirmative relief in order to prevent some future irreparable injury. See, e.g., 11A Charles A. Wright, Arthur R. Miller, and Mary K. Kane, Federal Practice and Procedure Sec. 2948 (1995).

VIII. Applying the Standard

1. The Court concludes that Plaintiffs are likely to succeed on their claims that:

(a) The Act, on its face and as applied to Plaintiffs, violates the First and Fourteenth Amendments, and the Commerce Clause of the United States Constitution.

(b) The Act violates the First and Fourteenth Amendments of the United States Constitution because it effectively bans speech that is constitutionally protected for adults.

(c) Defendants have failed to satisfy their burden to demonstrate that the Act will directly and materially advance a compelling governmental interest.

(d) Defendants have failed to demonstrate that the Act constitutes the least restrictive means of serving its stated interest.

(e) The Act violates the First and Fourteenth Amendments of the United States Constitution because it is substantially overbroad.

(f) The Act violates the First and Fourteenth Amendments of the United States Constitution because it prevents people from communicating and accessing information anonymously. (g) The exceptions set forth in the Act fail to ameliorate the above constitutional violations. See generally Reno, 117 S. Ct. 2329; Pataki, 969 F. Supp. 160.

(h) The Act violates the Commerce Clause of the United States Constitution because it regulates conduct occurring wholly outside the State of Michigan.

(i) The Act violates the Commerce Clause of the United States Constitution because it constitutes an unreasonable and undue burden on interstate and foreign commerce. See e.g. Pataki, 969 F. Supp. at 177-80 (noting that nature of the Internet makes the burdens on interstate and foreign commerce unreasonable in light of the limited benefits conferred locally); ACLU v. Johnson, supra.

(j) The Act violates the Commerce Clause of the United States Constitution because it subjects interstate use of the Internet to inconsistent state regulations. See e.g. Southern Pac. Co. v. Arizona, 325 U.S. 761, 767, 65 S. Ct. 1515, 89 L. Ed. 1915 (1945) (finding Arizona statute regulating length of trains violated Commerce Clause as it substantially impeded the free flow of commerce between the states).

(k) Plaintiffs have standing to bring this suit and to make this motion for preliminary injunction.

2. The Court concludes Plaintiffs have made a sufficient showing that they will suffer irreparable injury:

(a) At a minimum the curtailment of their constitutionally protected speech, if the preliminary injunction is not granted. See e.g. Elrod v. Burns, 427 U.S. 347, 373, 96 S. Ct. 2673, 49 L.Ed.2d 547 (1976) (holding that the "loss of First Amendment freedoms, for even minimal periods of time, unquestionably constitutes irreparable injury") (citing New York Times Co. v. United States, 403 U.S. 713, 91 S. Ct. 2140, 29 L. Ed. 2d 822 (1971)).

(b) Absent an injunction, as the Act violates the Commerce Clause of the United States Constitution.

3. Finally, the Court concludes that the preliminary injunction will not cause substantial harm to others, but rather will serve the public interest, because it will protect the free expression of the millions of Internet users both within and outside of the State of Michigan.

Having reached these findings of fact and conclusions of law, the Court concludes that the Plaintiffs have met their burden for a motion for a preliminary injunction. The threatened injury to Plaintiffs' constitutionally protected speech outweighs any claimed damage to the Defendants. Consequently, the Court grants the Plaintiffs' Motion for a Preliminary Injunction.

NOW, THEREFORE, IT IS HEREBY ORDERED THAT, pursuant to Fed. R. Civ. P. 65(d), the Defendants - as well as their officers, agents, servants, employees, and attorneys, and those persons in active concert or participation with Defendants - are hereby preliminarily enjoined from enforcing or threatening to enforce 1999 Public Act 33, which amends Sections 3, 5, 6 and 7 (Mich. Comp. Laws Secs. 722.673, 722.675, 722.676, and 722.677) of 1978 Public Act 33, M.C.L. Secs. 722.671- 722.684

<signed>
Arthur J. Tarnow
United States District Judge

Date: 7/29/99

Footnotes

[1] Law Clerk Philip M. Cavanagh provided quality research assistance.

[2] As defined in M.C.L. 722.673; M.S.A. 25.254(3), as amended.

[3] Plaintiffs here do not challenge the Act to the extent that it applies to obscenity. This would allow the Court to enjoin the amendments without nullifying the original statute.

[4] As support for this Court to accept the parties' stipulation of facts, the parties rely on the following cases as cited in the stipulation: Reno v. American Civil Liberties Union ("Reno"), 521 U.S. 844, 117 S. Ct. 2329 (1997), aff'g American Civil Liberties Union ("ACLU") v. Reno, 929 F. Supp. 824 (E.D. Pa. 1996); ACLU v. Johnson, 4 F. Supp. 2d 1029 (D. N.M. 1998), appeal docketed, No. 98-2199 (10 th Cir. Aug. 7, 1998); American Libraries Ass'n v. Pataki, 969 F. Supp. 160 (S.D. N.Y. 1997); ACLU v. Reno ("Reno II"), 31 F. Supp. 2d 473 (E.D. Pa. 1999), appeal docketed, No. 99-1324 (3 rd Cir. April 26, 1999).

[5] Defendants do not challenge that Plaintiffs satisfy the 2nd and 3rd criteria needed for standing as set forth Lujan.

[6] Hobson's choice: [After Thomas Hobson (1544-1631), English liveryman, from his requirement that customers take either the horse nearest the stable door or none.] An apparently free choice that offers no actual alternative. Webster's II, New College Dictionary 526 (1995)

[7] Defendants' sole argument was that the State of Michigan, by its police powers, could enact this statute as a constitutional ban on obscenity. Therefore, Defendants refused to recognize that the Act regulates free speech and must overcome strict scrutiny.

[8] Dr. Cranor also stated that she had done extensive research on solutions to crub unsolicited, unwanted e-mail. She labeled this junk e-mail problem as SPAM - a computer term which is not an acronym, but rather is named after a Monty Python comedy skit.

[9] Meyer v. Nebraska, 262 U.S. 390, 399, 43 S.Ct. 625, 626-627, 67 L.Ed. 1042 (1923) (recognizing liberty interest in raising children).

PRESS RELEASE

Cyberspace Communications, Inc.
P.O. Box 4432, Ann Arbor, MI 48103
Contact: Mary Remmers (734) 665-5388
mary@cyberspace.org

June 23rd, 1999, FOR IMMEDIATE RELEASE

Cyberspace Communications Joins ACLU to Block Censorship Law

ANN ARBOR, MICHIGAN -- Cyberspace Communications, Inc., an Ann Arbor-based non-profit corporation that operates the online community "Grex" (www.cyberspace.org), has joined a suit to block the implementation of Michigan Public Act 33 of 1999 (The Child Online Protection Act), which makes it illegal to transmit "sexually explicit" material to minors. The Act is scheduled to go into effect on August 1st, 1999. Other plaintiffs in the suit include the American Civil Liberties Union, Art on the Net, Web Del Sol, and the AIDS Partnership of Michigan. The ACLU's press release on the suit is available here.

Grex is an open-access online community, with a charitable mission and an all-volunteer staff, which hosts electronic discussions. It opposes the new law because the law is too broad (it would criminalize transmission over the Internet of many scenes which are shown on broadcast television), and it erodes the First Amendment right to free speech. It would also require that all discussion sites on the Internet validate the identities of all participants and censor any material which is visible to minors and of a "sexually explicit" nature. Validation and censorship would stifle a lot of healthy discussion, beyond what the law is meant to cover. And small "grass roots" organizations such as Grex, which cannot afford to pay validators or censors, would be forced to shut down.

THE LAW IS TOO BROAD

"It is an understandable desire to want to protect children from what some people see as unhealthy influences," said Mary Remmers, spokesperson for Cyberspace Communications. "We have existing laws about child pornography and obscenity to do that. This law, however, is broad enough that 'sexually explicit' material may include discussions of rape, AIDS, safe sex, pornography laws, prostitution, and other topics which people are entitled to discuss openly and frankly. The law encompasses even clinical discussions of sexual issues, not just material designed to shock and titillate."

"It would be bad enough if this were the only material affected, but a law to outlaw one kind of speech inevitably affects other kinds. People afraid of saying the wrong thing will avoid getting close to a topic that might get them in trouble. The result is a widespread 'chilling effect' on free speech."

ENFORCING THE LAW WOULD REQUIRE VALIDATION AND CENSORSHIP

"In order to avoid prosecution under this act, Grex would have to authenticate all users and censor sexually explicit material," said John Remmers, president of Cyberspace Communications. In cyberspace, unlike in person, it is impossible to tell who is a minor and who is not. To comply with the law, open-access discussion systems would be required to collect ID from every participant, and then to censor areas which are accessible to minors.

"One of the ways Grex fosters lively debate is by encouraging any and all to participate and share their point-of-view," said Mary Remmers. "Insisting participants first register, then wait for an ID check, then submit their comments to moderators who would filter for content, would clearly limit participation and stifle discussion."

"It's well-established legally that free speech isn't really free unless it can be made anonymously," said Mark Conger, a Cyberspace Communications board member. It is against Grex policy to censor content or to insist that people identify themselves. "We have found time and again that the best answer to speech you don't agree with is to rebut it, not to censor it."

VALIDATION AND CENSORSHIP ARE NOT FEASIBLE

Even if censorship were an acceptable solution, it would not be feasible for an organization the size of Grex. Grex is a "grass roots" institution run entirely by volunteers. Its 1998 income was approximately $8200, which came almost entirely from donations. (The IRS has designated Cyberspace Communications a 501(c)3 charitable institution, so donations are tax- deductible.) Almost all of that money goes to pay utility bills to keep the system running. Grex has no money to pay censors or validators, and yet it has 29,000 users who post about 200 long messages and 5000 short ones every day. It would be logistically impossible to get volunteers to do the work of censoring that material and validating the 200 people who create accounts daily.

Putting organizations like Grex out of business has long-range implications for free speech. "One of the great advantages of the Internet is that an organization like Grex with a shoestring budget can be home to a community of thousands of people," said Mary Remmers. "If only large organizations with lots of resources could afford to host discussion forums, then all discussion would be limited by the biases and agendas of those organizations. Pressure from advertisers and shareholders might influence their censorship decisions. Under those conditions, speech is no longer free."

Cyberspace Communications is a 501(c)3 charitable institution founded in Ann Arbor, Michigan in 1991. Its mission is to run the online system Grex (which means "group" in Latin) in order to foster free speech and community, and give Internet access to people who cannot afford to pay for it. Grex hosts forums on such topics as music, the arts, cooking, writing, consumer information, finance, small businesses, philosophy, living with disabilities, men's and women's issues, and games. Anyone with a computer and modem or access to the Internet can use Grex for free, anonymously if they wish. Funding comes almost entirely from donations, which are tax-deductible. Grex gets no money from advertising. Because Internet bandwidth is limited, users are not allowed to store pictures on Grex. For more information on Grex, visit http://www.cyberspace.org.